Guide to the William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: Manuscripts
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Box and Folder List, 1542-1967; 7.51; (18 boxes)
  - SHAWCROSS, JOHN, B. 1871
    - ALS: Duddleswell, Uckfield, Sussex, to Adolf Ingram Frantz, 1947 Oct 27 (Box 16, Folder 651)
      he is now working on the second part
      and hopes to publish both parts
      together - they came out in 1959.
  - SHUFORD, F. B.
    - ALS: Goethean Hall, Mercersburg, Pa., to James Gates Percival, New Haven, 1841 Dec 21 (Box 16, Folder 652)
      2 p.; 25 x 19 cm. with address.
      As secretary of the Goethean Literary
      Society of Mercersburg, Shuford
      requests permission to enroll
      Percival among its list of
      distinguished honorary members.
      With impressed blind seal of the
      Society bearing the head, in
      profile, of Goethe.
  - SOLMS-LAUBACH, HERMANN GRAF ZU, B. 1842
    - Die Bennettitienstämme der italienischen Museen von G. Capellini und H. Grafen zu Solms. II. Botanischer Theil von H. Grafen zu Solms (Box 16, Folder 653)
      AMs, 35, 3 l.; 22 x 18 cm.
      An excerpt from this manuscript was
      published in translation in G. R.
      Wieland's American fossil cycads,
      v. 1, 1906, p. 139-141.
      Enclosure: ALS: Yale University,
      George Reber Wieland to William
      Alfred Speck, June 23, 1924, 1 p.
      21 x 28 cm.
  - SONDERSHAUSEN, KARL, 1792-1882
    - ALS: Weimar, to "Hochzuverehrender Herr Geheimer Hofrath", 1845 Feb 10 (Box 16, Folder 654)
  - SORET, FRÉDÉRIC JACOB, 1795-1865
    - ALS, to Friedrich Wilhelm von Bielke, n.y. Jun 14 (Box 16, Folder 655)
    - Sur l'auteur en envoyant ce livre à Madame Ottilie d. Goethe, 1825 May 18
      - Autograph poem (in pencil), signed: F. S. Begins: Son regard bienveuillant a contemplé la terre.
      - IN: Bonstetten, Karl Viktor von. L'homme du midi et l'homme du nord. Genève, Paris, 1824, on front fly leaf (Yb B72 824).
  - SOUTHEY, ROBERT, 1774-1843
    - ALS: Keswick, to Mrs. Sarah Austin, 1833 Jul 4 (Box 16, Folder 656)
  - SPECK, SARA R.
    - William Alfred Speck, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 657)
      iii, 89 l.; 28 cm.
      Typescript (original and carbon).
      This biographical sketch by Mr.
      Speck's wife was used as the basis
      of Prof. C. F. Schreiber's version
      written for Goethe's works with the
      exception of Faust; a catalogue,
      v. 1, 1940.
  - SPECK, WILLIAM ALFRED, 1864-1928
    - ALS: New Haven, to Miss F. Turm, 1921 Nov 23 (Box 16, Folder 658)
      2 p.; 14 x 21 cm.
    - Autograph album. 1879-80
      - AMs, signed, 77 unnumb. l. (66 blank); 21 cm. Red cloth binding. 11 entries, dated May 19, 1879 to October 2, 1880. Teachers and classmates of Mr. Speck at Hoboken Academy, and a few friends have inscribed themselves. One quotation is from Wilhelm Meister.
      - See: Bound Volumes, folder 829
    - The Karl Berg Goethe Collection, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 659)
      AMs (in pencil), 40 p.; 23 x 15 cm.
      Note on accompanying envelope, in Mr.
      Schreiber's hand: Paper by Mr. Speck.
      A comprehensive description of the
      Berg Collection of 3,750 prints
      acquired by Mr. Speck in November
      1927.
      With typed transcription, 16 p.
  - SPOHR, LOUIS, 1784-1859
    - ALS: Cassel, to "Geehrter Freund", 1852 Apr 26 (Box 16, Folder 660)
    - ALS: Cassel, to the music publishers, Breitkopf & Härtel, 1836 Aug 9 (Box 16, Folder 661)
      2 p.; 26 x 22 cm., with address.
      From a Cassel dealer he has received
      the still remaining copies of the
      piano score of his Oratorio; he
      cannot agree to the price set by
      Breitkopf & Härtel for 2 manuscripts
      offered them for sale, but he is
      willing to write a song for their
      album by the middle of September
      requests a corrected proof of his
      Oratorio.
    - ALS: Cassel, to J. F. Schwenke, 1852 Apr 29 (Box 16, Folder 662)
      3 p.; 22 x 28 cm.
      Chiefly a detailed description of the
      conversion of his opera "Faust" into
      a grand opera for the production at
      Covent Garden, at the wish of Queen
      Victoria and Prince Albert.
    - ALS: Cassel, to L. Schlösser, 1853 Jan 21 (Box 16, Folder 663)
      2 p.; 22 x 27 cm.
  - SPURZHEIM, JOHANN GASPAR, 1776-1832
    - ALS, to the editors of Le Journal de la Société de la morale chrétienne, 1823 May 16 (Box 16, Folder 664)
      2 p.; 15 x 19 cm.
      Text in French.
      Letter mounted, with newspaper
      clippings and portrait on the
      same sheet, which has mourning
      With this letter is a printed article
      and portrait.
      Spurzheim was a phrenologist.
  - STAEL, MADAME DE (ANNE-LOUISE-GERMAINE), 1766-1817
    Full name: Anne Louise Germaine (Necker)
    baronne de Staël-Holstein
    - ALS (last page only), n.d. (Box 16, Folder 665)
      1 p.; 19 x 12 cm.
      Signed: M? Stael de N.
  - STAHL, ERNST LEOPOLD, 1882-
    - ALS: Heidelberg, to A. E. Richards, 1903 Dec 20 (Box 16, Folder 666)
      4 p.; 20 cm.
      Concerns the production of a series of
      performances of Faust plays,
      specifically of Marlowe's Doctor
      Faustus.
      With: Theater program of performance
      of Marlowe's Faust, under the
      auspices of the Heidelberger Hebbel-
      Verein, December 16-17, 1903, at
      Heidelberg.
      With: Hectographed list of activities
      of the Hebbel-Verein.
  - STAHR, ADOLF WILHELM THEODOR, 1805-1876
    - ALS: Oldenburg, to Dr. Johann Peter Eckermann, 1838 Jan 22 (Box 16, Folder 667)
      A request for permission to reprint
      a first version Weimar manuscript of
      Goethe's Iphigenie, for the purpose
      of comparing it with an Oldenburg
      manuscript. In 1839 Stahr issued:
      "Goethe's Iphigenie auf Tauris in
      ihrer ersten Gestalt."
  - STARK, JOHANN CHRISTIAN, 1753-1811
    - Autograph certificate attesting to the injuries suffered by the son of a Weimar soldier, Jena, 1801 Mar 13 (Box 16, Folder 668)
      1 p.; 24 x 19 cm.
      Stark was the physician of the Grand
      Duke Karl August.
  - STEDMAN, EDMUND CLARENCE, 1833-1908
    - ALS: New York, to Henry Phillips, 1881 Feb 23 (Box 16, Folder 669)
      A note of thanks for a copy of
      Phillips' translation of Chamisso's
      Faust, a dramatic sketch.
    - ALS: New York, to Mr. Warren, 1888 May 5 (Box 16, Folder 670)
  - STEIN, AMÉLIE CONSTANTINE L. H. (VON SEEBACH) VON
    Full name: Amalie Constantine Luise
    Henriette (von Seebach) von Stein
    - ALS: Weimar?, to "Liebe Gräfin", n.d. (Box 16, Folder 671)
      1 p.; 21 x 13 cm.
      Forwarding not only a signature, but
      also a picture of Goethe and a poem
      by him, as well as a few lines by
      Duke Karl August of Saxe-Weimar-
      Eisenach. These items are not
  - STEIN, CHARLOTTE ALBERTINE ERNESTINE VON, 1742-1827
    - ALS, to Karl Ludwig von Knebel?, 1820 Mar (Box 16, Folder 672)
      4 p.; 13 x 19 cm.
      Dated March 10 and 11, 1820.
  - STEIN, GOTTLOB ERNST JOSIAS FRIEDRICH, FREIHERR VON
    Dates: 1735-1793.
    - Document, signed: Weimar, to Friedrich III, Duke of Saxe-Weimar- Altenburg, 1765 Mar 8 (Box 16, Folder 673)
      Seal cut out.
      Formal request asking the duke to
      stand godfather to his first-born
      son, Gottlob Karl Wilhelm Friedrich.
  - STERLING, JOHN, 1806-1844
    - ALS: Bonn, to Mrs. Sarah Austin, 1833 Jun 14 (Box 16, Folder 674)
  - STIRLING, MRS. MARY ANNE, 1815-1895
    - ALS: 3 Duchess St., Portland Place, to Frederick Gye, [1864?] (Box 16, Folder 675)
      3 p.; 11 x 17 cm.
      Signed: Fanny Stirling.
  - STITH, CATHERINE (POTTER), 1795-1839
    - Autograph note on a printed announcement for the establishment of a seminary for young ladies, Philadelphia, 1826 Jan 2 (Box 16, Folder 676)
      1 p.; 25 x 21 cm.
      Requesting the return of this her
      "first essay in public life" from
      a Mr. Walsh.
  - STOLBERG, CHRISTIAN GRAF ZU, 1748-1821
    - ALS: Tremsbüttel, to Georg Joachim Göschen, 1786 Apr 3 (Box 16, Folder 677)
      Stolberg sends the manuscript of his
      "Otanes" to Göschen with a number of
      suggestions for printing: "Mit
      nächster Post soll auch der Säugling
      kommen, der hat nur etwas über 500
      Verse, ist also sehr klein."
  - STOLBERG, FRIEDRICH LEOPOLD GRAF ZU, 1750-1819
    - ALS: Hamburg, to unidentified recipient, 1784 Apr 26 (Box 16, Folder 678)
  - STOLBERG, F. L. VON GRAMM, GRÄFIN ZU, 1746-1824
    Full name: Friederike Luise (von
    Reventlow) von Gramm, Gräfin zu Stolberg
    - ALS: Tremsbüttel, to "Verehrter Lehrer", [1781?] Mar 4 (Box 16, Folder 679)
  - STORCH, LUDWIG, 1803-1881
    - ALS: Gotha, to Dr. Johann Peter Eckermann, 1839 Sep 2 (Box 16, Folder 680)
      2 p.; 21 x 26 cm.
      Personal green seal attached.
    - ALS: Gotha, to Dr. Johann Peter Eckermann, 1839 Sep 9 (Box 16, Folder 681)
      Enclosure: Manuscript note of book-
      title: Mariti Geschichte Fakkardins.
      Gotha, Ettlinger, 1790.
  - STORER, HORATIO ROBINSON, 1830-1922
    - 36 ALS, 10 autograph postcards: mostly from Newport, R.I., to William A. Speck, 1891-1916 (Box 16, Folder 682)
      With 3 envelopes.
      December 15, 1891 to June 30, 1916.
      Concerning Goethe and Schiller medals.
      Some letters accompanied by slips
      bearing embossed impressions of
      medals; on lower portion of letter
      of May 31, 1896 an impression of a
      Schiller medal.
      Letter of September 8, 1895 on
      stationery of Newport Sanitary
      Protection Association.
      With these letters is a printed list
      of H. R. Storer's published papers
      on numismatics.
      Storer was a gynecologist, medical
      numismatist, lecturer, and author of
      medical works.
  - SULLY, THOMAS, 1783-1872
    - ALS: London, to Catherine Potter Stith? in New Haven, Connecticut, 1838 Feb 14 (Box 16, Folder 683)
      Entreating Mrs. Stith to write down
      her meeting with Lord Byron for J.
      Wright's forthcoming book on the
      poet. Mrs. Stith apparently did not
      comply.
  - SWANWICK, ANNA, 1813-1899
    - ALS: Regents Park, London, to Miss F. P. O. - "My very dear friend", [1886?] Jul 10 (Box 16, Folder 684)
      6 p.; 10 x 15 cm.
  - TALMA, FRANCOIS JOSEPH, 1763-1826
    - Autograph note on an autograph bill for a decanter and goblets acquired from Nièce Complant F. Ouizille Gobert, [1792?] Nov 25 (Box 17, Folder 685)
      1 p.; 18 x 24 cm.
      Talma authorizes the payment of this
      bill.
  - TALVJ, 1797-1870
    Pen name for: Thérèse Albertine Louise (von
    Jacob) Robinson
    - ALS: Halle, to "Hochgeschätzter Herr", 1864 Nov 2 (Box 17, Folder 686)
      4 p.; 18 x 12 cm.
      On outside wrapper in another hand:
      "Therese Robinson, Amerikanerin, von
      Geburt aber eine Deutsche, schrieb
      unter dem Namen Talvj sowohl über
      slavische Sprachen als auch mit sehr
      guter Darstellung und gründlicher
      Kenntniss über die ersten
      Ansiedlungen in Amerika."
      On stationery with mourning border.
      Inquiry on living conditions at Weimar,
      where she intends to establish
      residence.
    - ALS: Halle, to Karl Gottfried Theodor Winkler (pseud. Theodor Hell), 1825 Dec 3 (Box 17, Folder 687)
      2 p.; 21 x 12 cm.
      Signed: Therese von Jakob.
  - TAUCHNITZ, CHRISTIAN BERNHARD FREIHERR VON, 1816-1895
    - ALS: Leipzig, to Mr. Marshall, 1887 Apr 22 (Box 17, Folder 688)
      2 p.; 20 x 12.5 cm.
      On mourning stationery.
      Concerns translations of Stella.
      Another letter, supposed to be
  - TAYLOR, BAYARD, 1825-1878
    - ALS: Kennett Square, Pennsylvania, to "Verehrte Frau", 1869 Dec 28 (Box 17, Folder 689)
      Black impressed monogram: BT.
      In German.
      Enclosure: Handwritten translation
      of letter.
    - ALS, to "My dear Arc", 1871 May 3 (Box 17, Folder 690)
    - ALS: New York, to Mrs. Anne Lynch Botta, 1864 Mar 15 (Box 17, Folder 691)
      Signed: Bayardo, detto il Cavaliere
      senza paura.
    - ALS: Kennett Square, Pennsylvania, to Mrs. Anne Lynch Botta, 1872 Apr 4
      - 1 p.; 12 x 20 cm.
      - IN: Goethe's Faust. 2 Th. Vor dem Palaste. Trans. by Bayard Taylor Box 7, folder 223
    - ALS, to Mrs. Anne Lynch Botta, 1878 Feb 18 (Box 17, Folder 692)
    - ALS: Kennett Square, Pennsylvania, to von Gerold?, 1871 Apr 17 (Box 17, Folder 693)
      With black impressed initials BT.
      Requesting the address of Frau von
      Goethe, to whom he wishes to send a
      copy of his translation of Goethe's
      Faust.
    - ALS: Kennett Square, Pennsylvania, to Paul Hamilton Hayne, 1871 Jan 13 (Box 17, Folder 694)
      Black impressed initials BT.
      Discussing the favorable reception the
      first part of his translation of
      Goethe's Faust received at the hand of
      the public, and his present labors on
      part two.
    - ALS: Cedarcroft, K. S., Pennsylvania, to Osgood, 1871 Jan 17 (Box 17, Folder 695)
      Notifying Osgood of his temporary
      address in New York, where he will
      remain until part II of Faust
      appears.
    - ALS: Kennett Square, Pennsylvania, to James Ripley Osgood, 1871 Nov 30 (Box 17, Folder 696)
    - ALS: Gotha, to James Ripley Osgood, 1872 Dec 16 (Box 17, Folder 697)
    - ALS: New York, to James Ripley Osgood, 1876 Oct 31 (Box 17, Folder 698)
    - ALS: Kennett Square, Pennsylvania, to Edmund Clarence Stedman, 1871 Apr 10 (Box 17, Folder 699)
    - ALS: Weimar, to Marie (Hansen) Taylor, 1873 Oct 16 (Box 17, Folder 700)
    - ALS: Weimar, to Marie (Hansen) Taylor, [1873 Oct 17?] (Box 17, Folder 701)
      Dated in pencil Oct. 17, 1873? Pencil
      note by Mr. Speck: Evidently Nov. 7.
    - ALS: Weimar, to Marie (Hansen) Taylor, 1873 Oct 17 (Box 17, Folder 702)
    - ALS: Weimar, to Marie (Hansen) Taylor, 1873 Oct 18 (Box 17, Folder 703)
    - ALS: Weimar, to Marie (Hansen) Taylor, 1873 Oct 28 (Box 17, Folder 704)
      Third paragraph of page inked out,
      probably by Mrs. Taylor; it was left
      intact in the photostat.
    - ALS: Weimar, to Marie (Hansen) Taylor, 1873 Nov 5 (Box 17, Folder 705)
    - ALS: Weimar, to Marie (Hansen) Taylor, 1873 Nov 7 (Box 17, Folder 706)
    - ALS: Weimar, to Marie (Hansen) Taylor, 1873 Nov 8 (Box 17, Folder 707)
    - ALS: Weimar, to Marie (Hansen) Taylor, 1873 Nov 9 (Box 17, Folder 708)
    - ALS: Weimar, to Marie (Hansen) Taylor, 1873 Nov 11 (Box 17, Folder 709)
    - 2 ALS: Weimar, to Marie (Hansen) Taylor, 1873 Nov 13 (Box 17, Folder 710)
      6 p.; 11 x 14 cm. and 22 x 14 cm.
      Account of his visit to Preller and
      other Weimar artists and scholars.
    - ALS: Weimar, to Marie (Hansen) Taylor, 1873 Nov 18 (Box 17, Folder 711)
      First leaf of letter, except date,
      cut away; the photostat is of the
      complete letter.
    - ALS: Weimar, to Marie (Hansen) Taylor, 1873 Nov 19 (Box 17, Folder 712)
    - ALS: New York, to Marie (Hansen) Taylor, 1875 Aug 29 (Box 17, Folder 713)
    - ALS: Gotha, to William Winter, 1872 Oct 6 (Box 17, Folder 714)
      4 p.; 13 x 23 cm.
    - Die Verloosung, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 715)
      Autograph poem, 2 p.; 21 x 13 cm.
      Begins: Jetzt da die Sachen alle
      bereit.
      Taylor signed it "Goethe" at the end,
      presumably thus indicating that his
      poem is in the style of Goethe's
      poetry, perhaps Hermann und
      Dorothea.
    - An Goethe, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 716)
      Autograph poem (original draft, in
      pencil), 3 p.; 7 x 11 cm.-
      15 x 11 cm.
      Begins: Erhabener Geist.
      The 3d stanza written on inside back
      cover detached from an unidentified
      book.
      Revised version published in many
      editions of Taylor's translation of
      With envelope bearing manuscript note
      explaining the origin of the poem,
      signed Lilian B. T. Kiliani, April
      30, 1920.
    - To Goethe. From the German of Bayard Taylor, 1900 Jul (Box 17, Folder 717)
      1 l.; 23 x 21 cm.
      Translation of Taylor's poem An Goethe,
      by Frank Claudy. The original German
      version appeared in Taylor's
      translation of Faust, 1871.
    - Der glückliche Tag ist vorüber, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 718)
      Autograph poem, 2 p.; 25 x 19 cm.
      Signed: B. T.
      Without title.
    - An das Burgfräulein Chriemhilde? Wegen dem Biere (Box 17, Folder 719)
      22 x 14 cm.
      First line: "Du, die hohe, holde."
      On p. 2, there are 2 other poems: "Der
      Tag ist rauh" and "An meine Frau."
    - Hier, unter wilden Griechen, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 720)
      Autograph poem, signed, 1 p.
    - A collection of poems, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 721)
      AMs, 24 p.; various sizes.
      Several poems in Mrs. Taylor's hand,
      and one composed by her, Dec. 20,
      1872.
      Contents: Da die Gläser sind noch
      nicht leer; Kennst du das Land, wo
      schönste Braten blühen (parody of
      Goethe's "An Mignon"); Abschiedslied
      Edles Paar, ihr habt vom tiefen
      Kelch des Lebens; Lieblich, sanft
      und milde; Ich wandl' auf deiner
      Pfad, Natur!; Nachdem der
      Neujahrstag war gekommen; Das Wetter
      (by Marie Taylor); Wohngedicht; Ich
      habe unausstehlichen Durst; Wer
      leidet an einem bösen Husten; Die
      durst'ge Erde trinkt den Regen
      Leidevoll, kreidevoll (parody of
      Goethe's "Freudvoll und leidvoll")
      Der Versuch deutsche Gedichte; Das
      Lied vom schläfrigen Manne; Gelobet
      sei Schlaf!; Er legt sich auf's Heu
      Die Hinterbliebenen traurig; Ich
      sitze in der Laube; An die liebe,
      gute Tante; Vom Nordkay.
    - Dank dir, theuerster Freund, 1873 Dec 27 (Box 17, Folder 722)
      Autograph poem, 1 p.; 27 x 21 cm.
    - Goethe, 1875 Aug 28 (Box 17, Folder 723)
      Autograph poem, signed, 6 p.
      25 x 20 cm.
      Begins: Whose voice shall so invade.
      Printed in the "Evening Post," "New
      York Tribune," "New York Herald,"
      and "The World" on August 30, 1875
      also in B. Taylor's Home pastorals,
      ballads and lyrics, 1875.
      A facsimile appeared as Facsimile and
      reproductions of unique or rare
      Collection of Goetheana, 1918, no. 4.
      In its issue of September 5, 1875, the
      "New Yorker Staatszeitung" published
      a German translation by Carl Theodor
      Erben.
    - Three autographed portraits of Bayard Taylor, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 724)
      1. Painted by T. B. Read, engr. by
      W. G. Jackman. 17 x 13 cm. Signed:
      Yours ever, J? Bayard Taylor.
      2. Daguerreotype by Brady, engr. at
      J. M. Butler's establishment.
      18 x 13 cm. Signed: Bayard Taylor.
      3. Clipping mounted. Signed: Very truly
      yours, Bayard Taylor. On its reverse
      side is mounted a landscape 'Yanina'
      drawn by C. Stanfield from a sketch
      by W. Page, engr. by E. Finden.
    - "Kennst du das Land?" (Box 17, Folder 725)
      Galley proof of article, corrected in
      Taylor's hand.
      Published in: The Mayflower,
      Washington, 1876, no. 2, p. 9.
      A study on the difficulty of
      translating Goethe's poem "Mignon."
    - Biographical sketch of Bayard Taylor, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 726)
      Printed clipping, signed, with his
      manuscript notes, 2 p.; 31 x 21 cm.
      The clipping is mounted on large sheet,
      which bears the notes of biographical
      data and is directed to "Dear
      E[dmund] C[larence] S[tedman]."
      The last date mentioned is 1876.
      Ends with a remark: engaged at present
      on a biography of Goethe.
  - TAYLOR, MARIE (HANSEN), 1829-1925
    - ALS: New York, to Paul Hamilton Hayne, 1881 Apr 2 (Box 17, Folder 727)
      Letter within black border.
      Discusses her proposed biography of
      her husband. It was published as
      Life and letters of Bayard Taylor,
      ed. by Marie Hansen-Taylor and
      Horace E. Scudder, Boston, 1884,
      in 2 volumes.
    - 9 ALS, to William Alfred Speck, 1910-25 (Box 17, Folder 727a)
      1910 Mar 6, New York.
      1910 Mar 18, Kennett Square,
      Pennsylvania.
      1910 Mar 30, New York.
      1912 Mar 22, New York.
      1914 Nov 15, New York.
      1920 Apr 4, Gotha, Germany; with
      1922 Feb 7, Partenkirchen; with
      1922 Feb 12, Partenkirchen; with
      1925 Feb 16; Partenkirchen.
      With: ALS from Lilian Bayard Taylor
      Kiliani to William Alfred Speck.
      Feb. 16, 1925. Partenkirchen.
      2 p.; 18 x 14 cm. All ten letters
      bear on Bayard Taylor's translation
      of Goethe's Faust and the whereabouts
      of Taylor's manuscripts.
    - Faust, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 728)
      AMs (in pencil), 18, i.e. 20, l.
      24 cm. (l. 12b: 15 x 15 cm.).
      Irregular paging: 12a-b added; l. 14
      has a passage inserted by pinning on
      a slip.
      Leaves 3, 6, 12a, 13, 16 have text on
      verso.
      Mrs. Taylor's recollections of her
      husband's labor on his translation
      of Goethe's Faust.
    - AMs (Box 17, Folder 729)
      2 p.; 14 x 10 cm.
      A statement about Taylor's intention
      to write a biography of Goethe.
  - TERRY, ELLEN, DAME, 1847-1928
    - ALS, to William Jefferson Winter, 1887 Jan 31 (Box 17, Folder 730)
      Head of Mephistopheles embossed in red.
      With an arrow pointing to the head of
      Mephistopheles: "Here's an old
      friend of yours come to wish you a
      jolly happy new year ... Your loving
      friend Margaret."
  - THIEL, WILHELM
    - ALS: Johanngeorgenstadt, to Georg Ehrhardt, 1903 Jul 22
      - 2 p.; 21 cm. Announcing shipment of Lippold's text of Faust puppet-play.
      - IN: Faust puppet-play, Box 4, folder 156
  - THOMAS, CALVIN, 1854-1919
    - ALS: New York, to William Alfred Speck, 1912 Mar 20 (Box 17, Folder 731)
      1 p.; 27 cm.
      Declining invitation to visit the
      Goethe scholar; since 1896, professor,
      Department of Germanic languages,
      Columbia University, New York.
  - THON, CHRISTIAN AUGUST, 1754-1829
    - ALS, to "Hochverehrter Herr Cammerdirector", 1820 Apr 29 (Box 17, Folder 732)
  - THORN, GUSTAV
    - ALS: Plauen i. V., to Georg Ehrhardt, 1904 Nov 10
      - 1 p.; 22 cm. Announcing shipment of 9 photographic plates intended for Ehrhardt's edition of Bonesky's Faust text, published 1905. Enclosure: Stub of parcel post shipment card of the same date.
      - IN: Faust puppet-play, Box 4, folders 153-153a
  - TIECK, JOHANN LUDWIG, 1773-1853
    - ALS: Dresden?, to Karl Eduard von Bülow, 1839 Oct 7 (Box 17, Folder 733)
      Invitation to a midday meal to meet
      Carl Lebrecht Immermann.
  - TRELAWNY, EDWARD JOHN, 1792-1881
    - 3 ALS, to Catherine Potter Stith, 1833-34 (Box 17, Folder 734)
      12 p.; 23 x 19 cm.
      Personal seals attached.
      1833 Dec 18, Charleston, S.C.
      1834 Oct 27, Philadelphia.
      1834 Nov 27, Philadelphia.
      Published in the South Atlantic
      Quarterly, v. 22, no. 1, 1923.
  - TÜRCKHEIM, ANNA ELISABETH (SCHÖNEMANN) FREIFRAU VON
    Dates: 1758-1817
    - AL: Strasbourg, to Johann Friedrich Schönemann, 1798 Aug 30 (Box 17, Folder 735)
      2 p. with address "A Monsieur J. F.
      Schönemann à Francfort."
      Introducing Madame de Lechner; but
      chiefly concerned with the proposed
      marriage of her daughter Lili with
      young Bernard.
  - ULMANN, ALBERT
    - ALS: Munich, to Dr. Johann Peter Eckermann, 1832 Apr 28 (Box 17, Folder 736)
  - UNIVERSITÄT WITTENBERG. VERWALTUNG
    - Receipt, printed form, filled in and signed, Wittenberg, 1806 May 19 (Box 17, Folder 737)
      1 p.; 11 x 20 cm.
      For rent paid by Dr. Prof. Schmidt
      signed by Christian Friedrich Wolff.
  - VARNHAGEN VON ENSE, KARL AUGUST LUDWIG PHILIPP
    Dates: 1785-1858
    - ALS: Berlin, to "Verehrtester Herr", 1850 May 24 (Box 17, Folder 738)
    - ALS: Berlin, to Carl Gustav Carus, 1831 Oct 28 (Box 17, Folder 739)
    - ALS: Berlin, to Johann Peter Eckermann, 1830 Mar 12 (Box 17, Folder 740)
      3 p.; 21 x 24 cm.
      Enclosure: "Vorschlag zu einem